Francis J. Uplegger papers, 1867-1964 (bulk 1917-1960)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Francis J. Uplegger papers, 1867-1964 (bulk 1917-1960)
MS 299
Uplegger, Francis J., 1867-1964
Includes correspondence, writings, Bible translations, sermons, reports, and audiotapes, chiefly from 1917-1960, of Francis J. Uplegger, 1867-1964, and his son, Alfred Uplegger, relating to their work as Lutheran missionaries on the San Carlos Apache Indian Reservation in Arizona.
5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Francis J. Uplegger was born in Rastozk, Germany on October 29, 1867, and died on the San Carlos Indian Reservation in Arizona on June 13, 1964. Educated in Germany, he emigrated to the United States at age nineteen and enrolled at Concordia Theological Seminary in St. Louis, Missouri. He was ordained pastor of Saint John's Congregation in Hermansfort, Wisconsin, in July, 1891 and continued an active preaching career until his retirement, nearly 70 years later, in February, 1961.
His son Alfred Uplegger followed in his father's footsteps by becoming a Lutheran minister. In 1917 he moved to Arizona to be a missionary to the Apache Indians on the San Carlos Reservation. Two years later Francis Uplegger joined him on the reservation and ministered there for the rest of his life.
Adept at languages, Francis quickly began to learn how to speak and write the Apache language. He went on to compile the first Apache dictionary. He also wrote approximately twenty-five Gospel hymns in Apache and translated several important Lutheran liturgical documents and portions of the Bible into Apache.
Held in high esteem by many of the members of the tribe, he was affectionately called "Old Man Missionary." He assisted the tribe in drawing up a constitution in 1930-31 that was later used as a model by several other tribes. In 1957 Concordia Theological Seminary conferred the degree of Doctor of Divinity upon him. Francis Uplegger was married to Emma Plass, who had come from Germany to be his bride in 1891. Their children were Dorothea, Gertrude, Johana, and Alfred.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical and Background Materials, 1892-1916
II. Mission Records, 1917-1964
III. Family Correspondence, 1901-1925
IV. Works, Alfred Uplegger, 1917-1964
V. Works, Francis Uplegger, c. 1920-c. 1960
Scope and Content Note
Includes correspondence, writings, Bible translations, sermons, reports, and audiotapes, chiefly from 1917-1960, of Francis J. Uplegger, 1867-1964, and his son, Alfred Uplegger, relating to their work as Lutheran missionaries on the San Carlos Apache Indian Reservation in Arizona.
The Biographical and Background Materials consist of photocopies of two magazine articles about the Upleggers and their work at the San Carlos mission and a photocopy of the newspaper obituary of Francis Uplegger. Also included are school-related materials from Alfred Uplegger's days as a student, and miscellaneous materials from Alfred's life prior to his move to Arizona in 1917.
The Mission Records, 1917-1964, consist of miscellaneous material, reports, and correspondence. The miscellaneous materials range from such items as song lyrics and baptismal certificates to architectural plans for new buildings. The reports were prepared by Alfred Uplegger and provided quarterly updates to the mission sponsors on such matters as numbers of new converts and the financial condition of the mission. The correspondence consists primarily of letters to and from Alfred Uplegger regarding activities at the mission and events on the reservation at large.
Many of the letters are to and from fellow Lutherans in Uplegger's home state of Wisconsin. Other letters involve business-related matters such as insurance accounts and supplies for the mission. Major correspondents include Edgar Guenther and Paul Brockmann.
The Family Correspondence, 1901-1925, consists of letters from Francis and Johana Uplegger to Alfred Uplegger, letters from other relatives, such as uncles and cousins, to Alfred, and letters from friends and acquaintances to Alfred. Some of the letters are written in German.
The Works of Alfred Uplegger involve sermons and miscellaneous material. The sermon-related material consists of notes and outlines of sermons and sermons on reel-to-reel audiotape. The audiotapes are in records carton boxes, separate from the written material in manuscript boxes. The miscellaneous material consists of items ranging from song lyrics to essays to Bible study outlines.
The Works of Francis Uplegger likewise involve sermons and a wide assortment of other items. Since he eventually learned to preach in Apache, there are sermon notes in both English and Apache. There are also portions of the Bible translated into Apache. Many of the audiotapes contain sermons preached in Apache by Francis, along with ones preached in English by Alfred. Included in his Works are also lessons on how to speak Apache and several short stories which he wrote, along with a longer narrative work entitled "The Desire of the Nations Among the Apache."
Some material in German and Apache.
Access Terms
Uplegger, Francis J., 1867-1964 -- Archives
Uplegger, Alfred -- Archives
Brockman, Paul
Guenther, Edgar
Evangelical Lutheran Mission -- (San Carlos, Ariz.)
Apache Indians -- Missions
Apache languages
Lutheran Church -- Missions -- Arizona
Missionaries -- Arizona -- Archives
Missions -- Arizona
San Carlos Indian Reservation (Ariz.)
Correspondence
Sermons
Reports
Container List
- Series I: Biographical and Background Materials, 1892-1916
  The first folder contains a history of the Evangelical Lutheran Mission among the Apache Indians on the San Carlos Reservation from 1892 to March, 1903; the articles of incorporation of the Joint Synod of Wisconsin, Minnesota, Michigan, and Nebraska; photocopies of two articles about the Upleggers; and the obituary of Francis Uplegger. The following three folders contain turn-of-the-century editions of Lutheran periodicals in German; class notes and school assignments belonging to Alfred Uplegger; and an assortment of items ranging from business cards to newspaper clippings to exercise instructions. All of these materials date from prior to the Upleggers' move to Arizona to become missionaries to the Apaches.
  - History of the Evangelical Lutheran Mission among the Apache; Articles of Incorporation of the Joint Synod of Wisconsin, Minnesota, Michigan and Nebraska; photocopies of magazine articles about the Uplegger family. 1892-March 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lutheran newspapers, in German. 1899-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Class notes and school assignments. c.1908-c.1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous items. c.1913-c.1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Mission Records, 1917-1964
  The first folder contains a wide variety of items, including drawings, invoices, certificates, and lyrics. The next two folders contain mission reports. The following twelve folders contain mission correspondence.
  - Miscellaneous. c.1917-c.1927 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reports. 1917-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reports. 1925-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. 1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. 1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. 1923 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. 1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. 1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. 1927 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. 1929-1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. 1950-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series III: Family Correspondence, 1901-1925
  The first folder contains letters from Francis Uplegger to various persons. The next two folders contain letters from Francis Uplegger to Alfred Uplegger. The third folder contains letters from Johana Uplegger to Alfred. The fourth contains letters from other relatives, such as uncles and cousins, to Alfred. The last two folders contain letters to Alfred from friends and acquaintances.
  - Francis Uplegger. 1901-1904 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Francis Uplegger (to Alfred Uplegger). 1912-1915 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Francis Uplegger (to Alfred Uplegger). 1917-1925 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Alfred Uplegger (from Johana Uplegger). 1913-1917 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Alfred Uplegger (from various relatives). 1914-1925 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Alfred Uplegger (from friends). 1904-1915 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Alfred Uplegger (from friends). 1916-1925 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series IV: Works, Alfred Uplegger, 1917-1964
  The first eleven folders contain sermon-related material, including outlines, illustrations, and Biblical texts. The last three contain miscellaneous material such as essays, lyrics, and lists. Reel-to-reel audiotapes of sermons by Alfred Uplegger, dating from 1957-1964, are available in boxes seven and eight.
  - Sermons. No Dates (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sermons. 1917-1921 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sermons. 1922-1925 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sermons. 1926 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sermons. 1927 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sermons. 1928 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sermons. 1929 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sermons. 1930 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sermons. 1931 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sermons. 1932 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sermons. 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous: Unarranged. No Date (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
- Series V: Works, Francis Uplegger, c.1920-c.1960
  Sermon outlines, including extensive translations of Biblical texts into the Apache language. Reel-to-reel audiotapes of sermons by Francis Uplegger, dating from 1957-c.1961, are available in boxes seven and eight. Most of these audiotape sermons by Francis Uplegger are in the Apache language. Among the stories, by far the lengthiest is the one entitled "The Desire of the Nations Among the Apache." It is nineteen chapters in length, and is partly an autobiographical account of Francis Uplegger's experiences with the Apache people and partly a theological essay about the spiritual beliefs of the Apache and the Apaches' place within the Christian framework of history. The other stories are much briefer, and are essentially works of fiction designed to illustrate and teach Biblical ethics and doctrines. One folder contains teaching material on the Apache language. Nearly all of the unarranged material consists of documents written by Francis Uplegger in German.
  - Sermons: Genesis to Deuteronomy. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sermons: Genesis to Malachi. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sermons: Gospel According to Matthew. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gospel According to Luke. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sermons: Gospel According to John. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sermons: Romans to Galatians. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sermons: Ephesians to Revelation. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sermons on various texts and topics. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sermons from the year 1956. 1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "The Desire of the Nations Among the Apache," chs. 1-4. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "The Desire of the Nations Among the Apache," chs. 5-7. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "The Desire of the Nations Among the Apache," chs. 8-12. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "The Desire of the Nations Among the Apache," chs. 13-19. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "The Engagement in the Church at Quidnors". c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Glennis". c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "The Judgment in the Green Court" - Part 2. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "The Oath and the Agreement". c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "A Remarkable Night at Quidnors". c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "A Visit at Nadowawigoning". c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "What Satisfies - Queries and Answers". c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Lessons on the Apache Language. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Unarranged. c.1920-c.1960 (Box 6, Folder 13-18)
  - Sermons on Audiotapes: Unarranged. 1957-1964
    - 20th Sun. After Trinity, unknown. (Box 7, Tape 1)
    - F.U. Apache 'Hagaedo shithgo zhodagae' A.U. English, 10/29/1958. (Box 7, Tape 1)
    - Pentecost San Carlos Arizona, F.U. Apache Song 15 'Ninlgiv DiNiv'goz dzonn Bika' No. 15, F.U. Apache Sermon, A.U. English Prayer for Sick, 1958. (Box 7, Tape 2)
    - Ninlgiv DiNiv'goz dzonn Bika' No. 15, F.U. Apache sermon, A.U. English sermon, 5/17/1959. (Box 7, Tape 2)
    - 92nd birthday party, Apache pot-luck in Surprise, 10/25/1959. (Box 7, Tape 3)
    - San Carlos Arizona, 3rd Sunday after Easter Jubilate, F.U. Apache sermon, 4/27/1958. (Box 7, Tape 4)
    - 5th Sunday after Easter Rogate, F.U. Apache sermon, A.U. English sermon, 5/11/1958. (Box 7, Tape 4)
    - F.U. Special Ordination 40 yrs., Rev. Sitz. and Dr. Koch, unknown, 3 tapes. (Box 7, Tape 5)
    - 18 Sun. after Trinity and Communion, 10/12-15/1958. (Box 7, Tape 6)
    - R.R's children singing, Rev. F.U. Apache song 'Hayah Dinh'ya', unknown. (Box 7, Tape 7)
    - F.U. Apache sermon, A.U. English sermon, 'Yushti-shikiyu', 9/7/1958. (Box 7, Tape 8)
    - Peridot school children. No.5 Nirgoztsann, No.15 Ninhliv, No. 21 Hayah-Dinhya, 5/15/1959. (Box 7, Tape 9)
    - Peridot Mission children Apache-English songs, 1955-1956. (Box 7, Tape 10)
    - Mission school children, unknown. (Box 7, Tape 11)
    - Peridot children Apache songs, 5/9-10/1956. (Box 7, Tape 12)
    - Pentecost - Entire Service, 5/1/1955. (Box 7, Tape 13)
    - F.U. sermon in-house, Apache songs in Englist, 4/1/1956. (Box 7, Tape 13)
    - Rev. Sitz. nd Rev. Uplegger, 65th Anniversary in the ministry, 10/28/1956. (Box 7, Tape 14)
    - Rev. F. Uplegger 9th Sunday after Trinity and 68th Anniversary of Ordination, 7/26/1959. (Box 7, Tape 15)
    - Easter Apache sermon, 3/29/1959. (Box 7, Tape 16)
    - Sunday after Easter, 'Ninhilg'iv diniv'goz dzonn biko', 4/5/1959. (Box 7, Tape 16)
    - Easter 1958, 4/6/1958. (Box 7, Tape 17)
    - Good Friday, F.U. Apache sermon, A.U. English sermon, unknown. (Box 7, Tape 18)
    - Easter Apache song 'Ninhlqiv di-niv'goz-dzonn bika' (Box 7, Tape 19)
    - Apache sermon (Pontius Pilate) lecture, Apache songs, Baptism - Esther May Sprengeler, 3/8/1959. (Box 7, Tape 20)
    - Judica, A.U. English sermon, 3/23/1958. (Box 7, Tape 21)
    - Palmarum, F.U. Apache sermon, 3/30/1958 (Box 7, Tape 21)
    - Palmarum Sunday, 3/22/1959 (Box 7, Tape 21)
  - Sermons on Audiotapes: Unarranged. 1957-1964 (Box 8)
    - Mission Festival - San Carlos Apache Indian Mission, Yushdih, Yushdih page 17, Sermon by Alfred Burdette, 10/23/1960 (Box 8, Tape 1)
    - Funeral service - San Carlos Lutheran Church, 6/18/1964. (Box 8, Tape 2)
    - I heard the voice, Glory be to the father, Sweet hour of prayer, He leadeth me, 10/11/1959. (Box 8, Tape 3)
    - Advent, Christmas/ F.U. Sermon Apache, Christmas program, 12/25/1958. (Box 8, Tape 4)
    - Rev F. Uplegger Sermon. Gift from Mr. La Mante, 11/11/1956-7. (Box 8, Tape 5)
    - 1st Sunday in Advent, Communion, Yushdih! Shikiyu, English Sermon, 11/30/1958. (Box 8, Tape 6)
    - 2nd Sunday in Advent, Apache Sermon, The coming of the lord, The signs of the time, 12/7/1958. (Box 8, Tape 6)
    - 1st Sunday in Lent, Yushdih! Shikiyu No. 17, 3/6/1960. (Box 8, Tape 7)
    - Apache song, Apache sermon, English sermon, 11/16/1958. (Box 8, Tape 8)
    - Advent Sunday - Try!, 12/1952. (Box 8, Tape 9)
    - 10th Sunday after Trinity, Communion, F.U. Apache Sermon - song 18, 8/2/1959. (Box 8, Tape 10)
    - F.U. Last, duck over!, Nov 1 - 8, 11/1959. (Box 8, Tape 11)
    - Gary Newman reading. Apache - English songs, Peridot children, 1959? (Box 8, Tape 12)
    - Ev. Luth. Mission, Advent Christmas. 2nd and 3rd Sunday in Advent,1962. (Box 8, Tape 13)
    - Sermon Apache. 2nd Sunday after Easter. All English. Mother's day Sermon, 05/1960. (Box 8, Tape 14)
    - Synod report. Rev Hartzell, 10/4/1959. (Box 8, Tape 15)
    - F. Uplegger, A. Uplegger. Rogate, Trinity. Ihidna! Ihidna! Apace sermon, English sermon, prayers, 5/3/1959. (Box 8, Tape 16)
    - Mission Festival. Rev. Marcus Nitz. Thanksgiving D.E.U. Apache and English songs, 10/20/1963. (Box 8, Tape 17)
    - F.U. Rogate Prayer. Apache sermon. English sermon, 4/6/1956. (Box 8, Tape 18)
    - Mother's day sermon A.U. Rogate Sunday, 5/3/1959. (Box 8, Tape 18)
    - 4th Sunday in advent. F.I. Algki/" Davh Ihe'yu Agodz'a", 12/1957. (Box 8, Tape 19)
    - Mission festival. Rev. H. C. Nitz, 11/11/1964. (Box 8, Tape 20)
    - Judica Sunday in lent. F.U. 92+ yrs old - preaching in Apache. A.U. English + liturgy, 1960. (Box 8, Tape 21)
    - Easter. A.U. Fergus Sneezy. No 16 Ihidna ! Life true life, 1964. (Box 8, Tape 22)
    - Sermons. F. Uplegger. Leprosy - thanks for new life. Da-Bighedu-Shith go zhovgo - No. 13. Always with delight 1, 09/1957. (Box 8, Tape 23)
    - Peridot children. Christmas songs. F.U. Apache and English, 12/19/1960. (Box 8, Tape 24)
    - Cut off first part of "The Glory" P. 16 Issisgoh Agolsihni. Algkidavh Tleyu Agodza P. 9, unknown. (Box 8, Tape 25)
    - F.U. sermon. Workers in the vineyard. Ap. Song 13 Ila bighdn Shitth go zhovgp. Listening to the gospel. A.U. sermon, 2/14/1960. (Box 8, Tape 26)
    - F.U. Glendale, unknown. (Box 8, Tape 27)
    - 3rd Sunday in advent. F.U. apache sermon F. U. English, 12/1957. (Box 8, Tape 28)
    - 16th Sunday after Trinity. F.U. Apache. A.U. English, 9/21/1958. (Box 8, Tape 29)
    - Peridot children. Bethy, unknown. (Box 8, Tape 30)
    - F.U. Apache songs. No. 13 Listening to the gospels. No. 15 Apache spring song. 5 peridot children, 5/14/1959. (Box 8, Tape 31)
    - Apache song and sermon. By Dr. F. Uplegger 91.5 yrs old. Blessings on my way, 4/26/1959. (Box 8, Tape 32)
    - Apache song and sermon. By Dr. F. Uplegger 90.5 yrs old. Where are you going? Apache song no. 21, 5/18/1958. (Box 8, Tape 33)
    - Apache sermon F. Uplegger. Apache song No. 6. He who made the earth. Heaven, 5/13/1956. (Box 8, Tape 34)
    - Come unto me, ye. Before thee, God, who? Etc., 6/7/1959. (Box 8, Tape 35)
    - 1st Sunday after Trinity. Nivgostzann. F.U. Apache sermon 91.5 yrs old. A.U. english sermon. (Box 8, Tape 36)